<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="basics_electronics_weight">
        <item>Module I - 10%</item>
        <item>Module II - 20%</item>
        <item>Module III - 15%</item>
        <item>Module IV - 15%</item>
        <item>Module V - 20%</item>
        <item>Module VI - 20%</item>
        <item>Text Book &amp; References</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="basics_of_civil_engineering">
        <item>General Introduction to Civil Engineering - Various disciplines of Civil engineering, Relevance of Civil engineering in the overall infrastructural development of the country.&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction to types of buildings as per NBC; Selection of site for buildings.&lt;br>&lt;br> Components of a residential building and their functions. Introduction to industrial buildings – office / factory / software development office / power house /electronic equipment service centre (any one related to the branch of study)&lt;br>&lt;br> Students have to visit one such building and submit an assignment about the features of any one of the listed building related to their branch (Not included for exam).</item>
        <item>Building planning - Introduction to planning of residential buildings- Site plan, Orientation of a building, Open space requirements, Position of doors and windows, Size of rooms; Preparation of a scaled sketch of the plan of a single storeyed residential building in a given site plan.&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction to the various building area terms - Computation of plinth area / built up area, Floor area / carpet area - for a simple single storeyed building; Setting out of a building.</item>
        <item>Surveying - Principles and objectives of surveying;&lt;br>&lt;br> Horizontal measurements – instruments used – tape, types of tapes; Ranging (direct ranging only) – instruments used for ranging.&lt;br>&lt;br> Levelling - Definitions, principles, Instruments (brief discussion only) - Level field book - Reduction of levels - problems on levelling (height of collimation only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Modern surveying instruments – Electronic distance meter, digital level, total station, GPS (Brief discussion only).</item>
        <item>Building materials - Bricks, cement blocks - Properties and specifications. &lt;br>&lt;br> Cement – OPC, properties, grades; other types of cement and its uses (in brief).&lt;br>&lt;br> Cement mortar – constituents, preparation.&lt;br>&lt;br> Concrete – PCC and RCC – grades.&lt;br>&lt;br> Steel - Use of steel in building construction, types and market forms.&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>Building construction – Foundations; Bearing capacity of soil (definition only); Functions of foundations, Types - shallow and deep (sketches only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Brick masonry – header and stretcher bond, English bonds – Elevation and plan (one brick thick walls only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Roofs – functions, types, roofing materials (brief discussion only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Floors – functions, types; flooring materials (brief discussion only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Decorative finishes – Plastering – Purpose, procedure.&lt;br>&lt;br> Paints and Painting – Purpose, types, preparation of surfaces for painting (brief discussion only).</item>
        <item>Basic infrastructure and services - Elevators, escalators, ramps, air conditioning, sound proofing (Civil engineering aspects only)&lt;br>&lt;br> Towers, Chimneys, Water tanks (brief discussion only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Concept of intelligent buildings.&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Chudley, R., Construction Technology, Vol. I to IV, Longman Group, England&lt;br> • Chudley, R. and Greeno, R., Building Construction Handbook, Addison Wesley, Longman Group, England&lt;br> • Gopi, S., Basic Civil Engineering, Pearson Publishers&lt;br> • Kandya, A. A., Elements of Civil Engineering, Charotar Publishing house&lt;br> • Mamlouk, M. S., and Zaniewski, J. P., Materials for Civil and Construction Engineering, Pearson Publishers&lt;br> • McKay, W. B. and McKay, J. K., Building Construction Volumes 1 to 4, Pearson India Education Services&lt;br> • Minu, S., Basic Civil Engineering, Karunya Publications&lt;br> • Rangwala, S. C., Essentials of Civil Engineering, Charotar Publishing House&lt;br> • Rangwala, S. C. and Dalal, K. B., Engineering Materials, Charotar Publishing house&lt;br> • Rangwala, S. C. and Dalal, K. B., Building Construction, Charotar Publishing house</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="basics_of_electrical_engineering">
        <item>Elementary concepts of electric circuits: Kirchhoff’s laws, constant voltage and current sources, formation of network equations by node voltage and mesh current methods.&lt;br.&lt;br> Matrix representation - solution of network equations by matrix methods, star-delta conversion (Analysis of resistive networks only). Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Magnetic circuits: MMF, field strength, flux density, reluctance, energy stored in magnetic circuits.&lt;br>&lt;br> Electromagnetic induction: Faraday’s laws, Lenz’s law-statically induced and dynamically Induced emfs- self-inductance and mutual inductance, coefficient of coupling.&lt;br>&lt;br> Alternating current fundamentals: Generation of alternating voltages, waveforms frequency, period, average and RMS values and form factor. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>AC Circuits: Phasor representation of alternating quantities- rectangular, polar and exponential forms. Analysis of simple ac circuits - concept of impedance. Power and power factor in ac circuits- active, reactive and apparent power. Solution of RL, RC and RLC circuits.&lt;br>&lt;br> Three phase systems: Generation of three phase voltages- advantages of three phase systems, star and delta connection, three wire and four wire systems, relation between line and phase voltages, line and phase currents. Three phase power measurement by two wattmeter method. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Generation of power: Block schematic representation of generating stations hydroelectric, thermal and nuclear power plants. Renewable energy sources. Power transmission and distribution: Typical electrical power transmission scheme, need for high voltage transmission, substation equipments, primary and secondary transmission and distribution systems.</item>
        <item>Transformers: construction of single phase and three phase transformers (core type only) – EMF equation, losses and efficiency.&lt;br>&lt;br> Electric Machines: D.C. Machines - Construction, types, principles of operation of dc motor, applications. AC Motors - Construction, principles of operation of single phase and three phase induction motor. Principle of operation of Universal motor.</item>
        <item>Tariff: Different types of LT and HT consumers, tariff schemes - uniform tariff and differential tariff.&lt;br>&lt;br> Wiring systems: Basic concepts of wiring (conduit wiring only), service mains, meter board and distribution board. Earthing of installations - necessity of earthing, plate &amp; pipe earthing, protective fuses, MCB, ELCB. Lamps: Different types of lamps - Incandescent lamps, fluorescent, mercury vapour, sodium vapour, metal halide and LED lamps.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bhattacharya, S. K., Basic Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineering, Pearson&lt;br> • Bird, J., Electrical Circuit Theory and Technology, Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group&lt;br> • Del Toro, V., Electrical Engineering Fundamentals, Prentice Hall of India.&lt;br> • Hayt, W. H., Kemmerly, J. E., and Durbin, S. M., Engineering Circuit Analysis, Tata McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Hughes, Electrical and Electronic Technology, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Mehta, V. K. and Mehta, R., Basic Electrical Engineering, S. Chand Publishing&lt;br> • Parker and Smith, Problems in Electrical Engineering, CBS Publishers and Distributors&lt;br> • Sudhakar and Syam Mohan, Circuits and Networks Analysis and Synthesis, Tata McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Suresh Kumar, K. S, Electric Circuits and Networks, Pearson Education</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="basics_of_electronics_engineering">
        <item>Evolution of Electronics, Impact of Electronics in industry and in society.&lt;br>&lt;br> Resistors, Capacitors: types, specifications. Standard values, marking, colour coding.&lt;br>&lt;br> Inductors and Transformers: types, specifications, Principle of working.&lt;br>&lt;br> Electro mechanical components: relays and contactors.</item>
        <item>PN Junction diode: Intrinsic and extrinsic semiconductors, Principle of operation, V-I characteristics, principle of working of Zener diode, Photo diode, LED and Solar cell.&lt;br>&lt;br> Bipolar Junction Transistors: PNP and NPN structures, Principle of operation, input and output characteristics of common emitter configuration, Typical specifications of low, medium and high power and frequency diodes and transistors, packaging.</item>
        <item>Rectifiers and power supplies: Block diagram description of a dc power supply ,Half wave and full wave (including bridge) rectifier, capacitor filter, working of simple zener voltage regulator, Principle of SMPS&lt;br>&lt;br> Amplifiers and Oscillators: Circuit diagram and working of common emitter amplifier, Block diagram of Public Address system, concepts of feedback, working principles of oscillators, circuit diagram &amp; working of RC phase shift oscillator.</item>
        <item>Analogue Integrated circuits: Functional block diagram of operational amplifier, ideal operational amplifier, inverting and non inverting amplifier, comparator.&lt;br>&lt;br> Digital ICs: Logic Gates.&lt;br>&lt;br> Electronic Instrumentation: Principle and block diagram of digital multimeter, principle of digital storage oscilloscope, principle and block diagram of function generator.</item>
        <item>Radio communication: principle of AM &amp; FM, frequency bands used for various communication systems, block diagram of super heterodyne receiver.&lt;br>&lt;br> Radar system: Principle, block diagram of pulsed radar.&lt;br>&lt;br> Satellite communication: concept of geo-stationary satellite, satellite transponder, advantages, principle of Global Positioning System.</item>
        <item>Mobile communication: basic principles of cellular communications, concepts of cells, frequency reuse, principle and block diagram of GSM.&lt;br>&lt;br> Optical communication: block diagram of the optical communication system, principle of light transmission through fiber, advantages of optical communication systems.&lt;br>&lt;br> Entertainment and Security Electronics Technology: Basic principles of cable TV, CCTV, DTH system, HDTV, Plasma, LCD, LED TV.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bell, D. A., Electronic Devices and Circuits, Oxford University Press&lt;br> • Boylested, R. L. and Nashelsky, L., Electronic Devices and Circuit Theory, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Frenzel, L. E., Principles of Electronic Communication Systems, Mc Graw Hill&lt;br> • Kennedy, G. and Davis, B., Electronic Communication Systems, Mc Graw Hill&lt;br> • Tomasy, W., Advanced Electronic Communication system, PHI Publishers&lt;br></item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="basics_of_mechanical_engineering">
        <item>Thermodynamics: Laws of Thermodynamics, significance and applications of laws of thermodynamics; entropy, available energy; Clausius inequality; principle of increase of entropy; Ideal and real gas equations; Analysis of Carnot cycle, Otto cycle , Diesel cycle and Brayton cycle; Efficiency of these cycles.</item>
        <item>Energy conversion devices: Boilers, Steam turbines, Gas turbines and Hydraulic turbines; Working principle of two stroke and four stroke I.C. Engines (Diesel and Petrol), Reciprocating and centrifugal pumps, rotary pumps, reciprocating and centrifugal compressors, fans, blowers, rotary compressors; Air motor.</item>
        <item>Refrigeration and Air Conditioning: Vapour compression and absorption refrigeration systems, COP, Study of household refrigerator, Energy Efficiency Rating, Psychrometry, Psychrometric processes, window air conditioner, split air conditioner. Ratings and selection criteria of above devices. Refrigerants and their impact on environment.</item>
        <item>Engines and Power Transmission Devices in Automobiles, Different types of engines used in automobiles, types of automobiles; major components and their functions (Description only); Fuels; Recent developments: CRDI, MPFI, Hybrid engines. Belts and belt drives; Chain drive; Rope drive; Gears and gear trains; friction clutch (cone and single plate), brakes (types and applications only); Applications of these devices.</item>
        <item>Materials and manufacturing processes: Engineering materials, Classification, properties, Alloys and their Applications; Casting, Sheet metal forming, Sheet metal cutting, Forging, Rolling, Extrusion, Metal joining processes - Powder metallurgy.</item>
        <item>Machine Tools (Basic elements, Working principle and types of operations) Lathe – Centre Lathe, Drilling Machine – Study of Pillar drilling machine, Shaper, planer, slotter, Milling Machine, Grinding machine, Power saw; Introduction to NC and CNC machines.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Balachandran, Basic Mechanical Engineering, Owl Books&lt;br> • Benjamin, J., Basic Mechanical Engineering, Pentex Books&lt;br> • Clifford, M., Simmons, K. and Shipway, P., An Introduction to Mechanical Engineering Part I - CRC Press&lt;br> • Crouse, Automobile Engineering, Tata Mc-Graw-Hill, New Delhi&lt;br> • Gill, Smith and Zuirys, Fundamentals of IC Engines, Oxford and IBH publishing company Pvt. Ltd. New Delhi. Crouse, Automobile Engineering, Tata Mc-Graw-Hill, New Delhi.&lt;br> • Nag, P. K., Basic and Applied Thermodynamics, Tata McGraw-Hill&lt;br> • Pravin Kumar, Basic Mechanical Engineering&lt;br> • Roy and Choudhary, Elements of Mechanical Engineering, Media Promoters &amp; Publishers Pvt. Ltd., Mumbai.&lt;br> • Sawhney, G. S., Fundamentals of Mechanical Engineering, PHI</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="calculus">
        <item>Single Variable Calculus and Infinite series (Book I –sec.6.1, 6.4,6.8, 9.3, 9.5, 9.6, 9.8)&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction: Hyperbolic functions and inverses-derivatives and integrals.&lt;br>&lt;br> Basic ideas of infinite series and convergence.Convergence tests-comparison, ratio, root tests (withoutproof). Absolute convergence. Maclaurins series-Taylor series - radius of convergence.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only:Sketching, plotting and interpretation of exponential,logarithmic and hyperbolic functions using suitable software. Demonstration of convergence of series by software packages)</item>
        <item>Three dimensional space and functions of more than one variable (Book I – 11.7, 11.8, 13.1, 13.2)&lt;br>&lt;br> Three dimensional space; Quadric surfaces, Rectangular,Cylindrical and spherical coordinates, Relation between coordinate systems.Equation of surfaces in cylindrical and spherical coordinate systems.&lt;br>&lt;br> Functions of two or more variables – graphs of functions of two variables- level curves and surfaces –Limits and continuity.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Tracing of surfaces- graphing quadric surfaces- graphing functions of two variables using software packages)</item>
        <item>Partial derivatives and its applications(Book I –sec. 13.3 to 13.5 and 13.8)&lt;br>&lt;br> Partial derivatives - Partial derivatives of functions of more than two variables - higher order partial derivatives - differentiability, differentials and local linearity.&lt;br>&lt;br> The chain rule - Maxima and Minima of functions of two variables - extreme value theorem (without proof)- relative extrema.</item>
        <item>Calculus of vector valued functions(Book I-12.1-12.6, 13.6,13.7)&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction to vector valued functions - parametric curves in 3-space. Limits and continuity - derivatives - tangent lines - derivative of dot and cross product definite integrals of vector valued functions.&lt;br>&lt;br> Change of parameter - arc length - unit tangent - normal - velocity - acceleration and speed - Normal and tangential components of acceleration.&lt;br>&lt;br> Directional derivatives and gradients-tangent planes and normal vectors.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Graphing parametric curves and surfaces using software packages)</item>
        <item>Multiple integrals (Book I-sec. 14.1, 14.2, 14.3, 14.5, 14.6, 14.7)&lt;br>&lt;br> Double integrals - Evaluation of double integrals - Double integrals in non-rectangular coordinates - reversing the order of integration.&lt;br>&lt;br> Area calculated as double integral - Double integrals in polar coordinates.&lt;br>&lt;br> Triple integrals - volume calculated as a triple integral - triple integrals in cylindrical and spherical coordinates.&lt;br>&lt;br> Converting triple integrals from rectangular to cylindrical coordinates - converting triple integrals from rectangular to spherical coordinates - change of variables in multiple integrals - Jacobians (applications of results only)</item>
        <item>Vector integration(Book I sec. 15.1, 15.2, 15.3, 15.4, 15.6, 15.7, 15.8)&lt;br>&lt;br> Vector and scalar fields- Gradient fields – conservative fields and potential functions – divergence and curl - the ∇operator - the Laplacian ∇^2&lt;br>&lt;br> Line integrals - work as a line integral- independence of path-conservative vector field.&lt;br>&lt;br> Green’s Theorem (without proof- only for simply connected region in plane), surface integrals – Divergence Theorem (without proof) , Stokes’ Theorem (without proof) (For practice and submission as assignment only: graphical representation of vector fields using software packages) Green’s Theorem (without proof- only for simply connected region in plane), surface integrals – flux integral - Divergence Theorem (without proof) , Stokes’ Theorem (without proof) (For practice and submission as assignment only: graphical representation of vector fields using software packages )</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Text Book:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Anton, Bivens and Davis, Calculus, John Wiley and Sons.&lt;br> • Pal, S. and Bhunia, S. C., Engineering Mathematics, Oxford University Press, 2015.&lt;br> • Thomas Jr., G. B., Weir, M. D. and Hass, J. R., Thomas’ Calculus, Pearson.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>References:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bali, N. P. and Goyal, M., Engineering Mathematics, Lakshmy Publications.&lt;br> • Grewal, B. S., Higher Engineering Mathematics, Khanna Publishers, New Delhi. • Jordan, D. W. and Smith, P., Mathematical Techniques, Oxford University Press.&lt;br> • Kreyszig, E., Advanced Engineering Mathematics, Wiley India edition.&lt;br> • Sengar and Singh, Advanced Calculus, Cengage Learning.&lt;br> • Srivastava, A. C. and Srivasthava, P. K., Engineering Mathematics Vol. 1, PHI Learning Pvt.Ltd.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="common_weight">
        <item>Module I - 15%</item>
        <item>Module II - 15%</item>
        <item>Module III - 15%</item>
        <item>Module IV - 15%</item>
        <item>Module V - 20%</item>
        <item>Module VI - 20%</item>
        <item>Text Book &amp; References</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="course_no">
        <item>MA 101</item>
        <item>PH 100</item>
        <item>CY 100</item>
        <item>BE 100</item>
        <item>BE 110</item>
        <item>BE 101-01</item>
        <item>BE 101-02</item>
        <item>BE 101-03</item>
        <item>BE 101-04</item>
        <item>BE 101-05</item>
        <item>BE 101-06</item>
        <item>BE 103</item>
        <item>CE 100</item>
        <item>ME 100</item>
        <item>EE 100</item>
        <item>EC 100</item>
        <item>MA102</item>
        <item>BE102</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="credit">
        <item>3-1-0-4</item>
        <item>3-1-0-4</item>
        <item>3-1-0-4</item>
        <item>3-1-0-4</item>
        <item>1-1-2-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-0-1-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>2-1-0-3</item>
        <item>3-1-0-4</item>
        <item>2-0-2-3</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="design_and_engineering">
        <item>Design and its objectives; Design constraints, Design functions, Design means and Design from; Role of Science, Engineering and Technology in design; Engineering as a business proposition; Functional and Strength Designs. Design form, function and strength;&lt;br>&lt;br> How to initiate creative designs? Initiating the thinking process for designing a product of daily use. Need identification; Problem Statement; Market survey customer requirements; Design attributes and objectives; Ideation; Brain storming approaches; arriving at solutions; Closing on to the Design needs.&lt;br>&lt;br> An Exercise in the process of design initiation. A simple problem is to be taken up to examine different solutions Ceiling fan? Group Presentation and discussion.</item>
        <item>Design process- Different stages in design and their significance; Defining the design space; Analogies and “thinking outside of the box”; Quality function deployment-meeting what the customer wants; Evaluation and choosing of a design.&lt;br>&lt;br> Design Communication; Realization of the concept into a configuration, drawing and model. Concept of “Complex is Simple”. Design for function and strength. Design detailing- Material selection, Design visualisation- Solid modelling; Detailed 2D drawings; Tolerancing; Use of standard items in design; Research needs in design; Energy needs of the design, both in its realization and in the applications.&lt;br>&lt;br> An exercise in the detailed design of two products (Stapler/ door/clock)</item>
        <item>Prototyping- rapid prototyping; testing and evaluation of design; Design modifications; Freezing the design; Cost analysis.&lt;br>&lt;br> Engineering the design – From prototype to product. Planning; Scheduling; Supply chains; inventory; handling;manufacturing/construction operations; storage; packaging; shipping; marketing; feed-back on design.&lt;br>&lt;br> List out the standards organizations. Prepare a list of standard items used in any engineering specialization. Develop any design with over 50% standard items as parts.</item>
        <item>Design for “X”; covering quality, reliability, safety, manufacturing/construction, assembly, maintenance, logistics, handling; disassembly; recycling; re-engineering etc.&lt;br>&lt;br> List out the design requirements(x) for designing a rocket shell of 3 meter diameter and 8 meter length.&lt;br>&lt;br> Design mineral water bottles that could be packed compactly for transportation.</item>
        <item>Product centred and user centred design. Product centred attributes and user centred attributes. Bringing the two closer. Example: Smart phone. Aesthetics and ergonomics.&lt;br>&lt;br> Value engineering, Concurrent engineering, Reverse engineering in design; Culture based design; Architectural designs; Motifs and cultural background; Tradition and design;&lt;br>&lt;br> Study the evolution of Wet grinders; Printed motifs; Role of colours in design.&lt;br>&lt;br> Make sharp corners and change them to smooth curves check the acceptance. Examine the possibility of value addition for an existing product.</item>
        <item>Modular design; Design optimization; Intelligent and autonomous products; User interfaces; communication between products; autonomous products; internet of things; human psychology and the advanced products. Design as a marketing tool; Intellectual Property rights – Trade secret; patent; copy-right; trademarks; product liability.&lt;br>&lt;br> Group presentation of any such products covering all aspects that could make or mar it.&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Balmer, R. T., Keat, W. D., Wise, G., and Kosky, P., Exploring Engineering, Third Edition: An Introduction to Engineering and Design - [Part 3 - Chapters 17 to 27], ISBN- 13: 978-0124158917 ISBN-10: 0124158919&lt;br> • Dym, C. L., Little, P. and Orwin, E. J., Engineering Design - A Project based introduction - Wiley, ISBN-978-1-118-32458-5&lt;br> • Eastman, C. M. (Ed.), Design for X Concurrent engineering imperatives, 1996, XI, 489 p. ISBN 978-94-011-3985-4 Springer&lt;br> • Haik, Y. And Shahin, M. T., Engineering Design Process, Cengage Learning, ISBN-13: 978-0-495-66816-9&lt;br> • Pahl, G., Beitz, W., Feldhusen, J. and Grote, K. H., Engineering Design: A Systematic Approach, 3rd ed. 2007, XXI, 617p., ISBN 978-1-84628-319-2&lt;br> • Voland, G., Engineering by Design, ISBN 978-93-325-3505-3, Pearson India&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>Web pages:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • E-Book (Free download): http://opim.wharton.upenn.edu/~ulrich/designbook.html&lt;br> • http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/wmg/ftmsc/modules/modulelist/peuss/designforx/design_for_x_notes_section_5.pdf</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="differential_equations">
        <item>HOMOGENEOUS LINEAR DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS&lt;br> (Text Book 1: Sections: 1.7, 2.1, 2.2,2.4,2.6, 3.1, 3.2)&lt;br>&lt;br> Existence and Uniqueness theorem for solutions of initial value problems (without proof). Basic theory of solutions of homogeneous differential equations (superposition principle, basis of solutions, general and particular solutions).&lt;br>&lt;br> Methods of solving homogeneous linear differential equations with constant coefficients of orders two or higher. Modelling of free oscillations of a mass-spring system.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only:&lt;br> Solutions of separable, exact and first order linear differential equations and orthogonal trajectories )</item>
        <item>NON-HOMOGENEOUS LINEAR ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS&lt;br> (Text Book 1: Sections: 2.7—2.10, 3.3)&lt;br>&lt;br> Basic theory of non-homogeneous linear differential equations. Methods of solving non-homogeneous linear differential equations with constant coefficients&lt;br>&lt;br> Method of undetermined coefficients and method of variation of parameters.&lt;br>&lt;br> Legendre and Cauchy’s differential equations.&lt;br> Modelling of forced oscillations of mass-spring system and electric circuits.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Sketching, plotting and interpretation of solutions of differential equations using suitable software packages)</item>
        <item>NUMERICAL SOLUTIONS OF DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS&lt;&lt;br> (Text Book 1: sections 21.1, 21.2)&lt;br>&lt;br> Basic idea of numerical solutions of differential equations. Euler-method, improved Euler method, Runge-kutta method of fourth order (without proof)&lt;br>&lt;br> Predictor-corrector method of Adams-Moulton (without proof). Error bounds of these methods.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Implementation of the above numerical methods in any programming language or using software packages)</item>
        <item>FOURIER SERIES&lt;br> (Text Book 1: Sections: 11.1-11.2 )&lt;br>&lt;br> Periodic Functions- Orthogonality of Sine and Cosine functions-Fourier series of periodic functions, Euler’s formula, Condition for Convergence of Fourier series (without proof)&lt;br>&lt;br> Fourier series for even and odd functions, Half range expansion&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Plots of partial sums of Fourier series and demonstration of convergence using plotting software)</item>
        <item>PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATION&lt;br> (Text Book 2: Section: 5.1.1, 5.1.2, 5.1.3, 5.1.4, 5.1.5, 5.1.9, 5.1.10, 5.2.6, 5.2.7, 5.2.8, 5.2.9, 5.2.10)&lt;br>&lt;br> Formation of PDEs, solutions of first order PDEs, General integral, complete integral, Lagrange’s linear equation,&lt;br>&lt;br> Higher order PDE-Solution of Linear Homogeneous PDE with Constant Coefficients.</item>
        <item>APPLICATIONS OF PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS&lt;br> (Text Book 2: Section: 6.1, 6.2, 6.3, 6.4, 6.7, 6. 8, 6. 9, 6.9.1, 6.9.2)&lt;br>&lt;br> Method of Separation of Variables&lt;br>&lt;br> Modelling Vibrations of a Stretched sting-One dimensional wave equation and its Solution by Fourier series.&lt;br>&lt;br> Heat transfer through an insulated rod-one dimensional heat equation. Solution of heat equation by Fourier series in special cases– insulated rod with ends at zero temperatures, insulated rod with ends at non-zero temperatures.&lt;br>&lt;br> (For practice and submission as assignment only: Plots of partial sums of Fourier series solutions of PDEs and demonstration of convergence using plotting software)</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Text Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Kreyszig, E., Advanced Engineering Mathematics, Wiley&lt;br> • Srivastava, A. C. and Srivasthava, P. K., Engineering Mathematics, Vol 2. PHI Learning Pvt.Ltd.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bali, N. P. and Goyal, M., Engineering Mathematics, Lakshmy Publications&lt;br> • Datta, Mathematical Methods for Science and Engineering. Cengage Learning&lt;br> • Edwards, C. H. and Penney, D. E., Differential Equations and Boundary Value Problems. Computing and Modelling, Pearson.&lt;br> • Grewal, B. S., Higher Engineering Mathematics, Khanna Publishers, New Delhi.&lt;br> • Jordan, D. W. and Smith, P., Mathematical Techniques, Oxford University Press&lt;br> • Pal, S and Bhunia, S. C., Engineering Mathematics, Oxford, 2015&lt;br> • Ross, S. L., Differential Equations, Wiley</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="engineering_chemistry">
        <item>Spectroscopy: Introduction, Beer Lamberts Law (worked out examples)&lt;br>&lt;br> UV-visible spectroscopy - Principle, Instrumentation and applications&lt;br>&lt;br> IR spectroscopy - Principle and applications&lt;br>&lt;br> 1H NMR spectroscopy - Principle, chemical shift - spin - spin splitting and applications including MRI&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>Electrochemistry: Different types of electrodes (general) – SHE, Calomel electrode, Glass electrode and determination of E0 using SHE &amp; Calomel electrode&lt;br>&lt;br> Electrochemical series and its applications.&lt;br>&lt;br> Nernst equation for an electrode- Derivation, application &amp; numericals&lt;br>&lt;br> Potentiometric titration - Acid-base and redox titration&lt;br>&lt;br> Lithium ion cell and Fuel cell.</item>
        <item>Instrumental Methods: Thermal analysis - Principle, instrumentation and applications of TGA and DTA.&lt;br>&lt;br> Chromatographic methods - Basic principles, column, TLC. Instrumentation and principles of GC and HPLC.&lt;br>&lt;br> Conductivity - Measurement of conductivity</item>
        <item>Chemistry of Engineering Materials: Copolymers - BS, ABS - Structure and Properties.&lt;br>&lt;br> Conducting Polymers - Polyaniline, Polypyrrole - Preparation, Structure and Properties.&lt;br>&lt;br> OLED – An introduction&lt;br>&lt;br> Advanced Polymers – Kevlar, Polybutadiene rubber and silicone rubber: Preparation, Structure and Properties.&lt;br>&lt;br> Nanomaterials – Definition, Classification, chemical methods of preparation - hydrolysis and reduction&lt;br>&lt;br> Properties and Applications – Carbon Nano Tubes and fullerenes.</item>
        <item>Fuels and Lubricants: Fuels - Calorific Value, HCV and LCV - Determination of calorific value of a solid and liquid fuel by Bomb calorimeter - Dulongs formula and Numericals.&lt;br>&lt;br> Liquid fuel - Petrol and Diesel - Octane number &amp; Cetane number&lt;br>&lt;br> Biodiesel - Natural gas.&lt;br>&lt;br> Lubricant - Introduction, solid, semisolid and liquid lubricants.&lt;br>&lt;br> Properties of lubricants - Viscosity Index, Flash point, Fire point, Cloud point, Pour point and Aniline point.</item>
        <item>Water Technology: Types of hardness, Units of hardness, Estimation of Hardness – EDTA method. Numericals based on the above&lt;br>&lt;br> Water softening methods - Ion exchange process - Principle. Polymer ion exchange.&lt;br>&lt;br. Reverse Osmosis - Disinfection method by chlorination and UV&lt;br>&lt;br> Dissolved oxygen, BOD and COD.&lt;br>&lt;br> Sewage water Treatment - Trickling Filter and UASB process.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Ahad, J., Engineering Chemistry, Jai Publications&lt;br> • Dara, S. S., Engineering Chemistry, S Chand Publishers&lt;br> • Fernandez, A., Engineering Chemistry, Owl Book Publishers, ISBN 9788192863382&lt;br> • Jain and Jain, Engineering Chemistry, Dhanpat Rai Publishers&lt;br> • Kaurav, Engineering Chemistry with Laboratory Experiments. PHI, ISBN 9788120341746&lt;br> • Manjooran K. S., Modern Engineering Chemistry, Kannatheri Publication&lt;br> • Seymour, R. B., Introduction to Polymer Chemistry, McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Rath, P., Engineering Chemistry, Cengage Learning, ISBN 9788131526699&lt;br> • Wiley India, Engineering Chemistry, ISBN 9788126543205</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="engineering_graphics">
        <item>6 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction to Engineering Graphics: Need for engineering drawing. Drawing instruments; BIS code of practice for general engineering drawing.&lt;br>&lt;br> Orthographic projections of points and lines:-Projections of points in different quadrants; Projections of straight lines inclined to one of the reference planes, straight lines inclined to both the planes; True length and inclination of lines with reference planes; Traces of lines.</item>
        <item>12 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Orthographic projections of solids:-Projections of simple solids* in simple positions, projections of solids with axis inclined to one of the reference planes and axis inclined to both the reference planes.</item>
        <item>12 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Isometric Projections:-Isometric projections and views of plane figures simple* and truncated simple* solids in simple position including sphere and hemisphere and their combinations.&lt;br> Freehand sketching: Freehand sketching of real objects, conversion of pictorial views into orthographic views and vice versa.</item>
        <item>6 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Introduction to Computer Aided Drafting - familiarizing various coordinate systems and commands used in any standard drafting software - drawing of lines, circle, polygon, arc, ellipse, etc. Creating 2D drawings. Transformations: move, copy, rotate, scale, mirror, offset and array; trim, extend, fillet, chamfer.&lt;br> Dimensioning and text editing. Exercises on basic drafting principles, to create technical drawings. Create orthographic views of simple solids from pictorial views. Create isometric views of simple solids from orthographic views. Solid modelling and sectioning of solids, extraction of 2D drawings from solid models. (For internal examination only, not for University Examination).</item>
        <item>9 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Sections and developments of solids: - Sections of simple* solids in simple vertical positions with section plane inclined to one of the reference planes - True shapes of sections. Developments of surfaces of these solids.</item>
        <item>6 exercises&lt;br>&lt;br> Intersection of surfaces: - Intersection of prism in prism and cylinder in cylinder - axis bisecting at right angles only. Perspective projections: - perspective projections of simple* solids.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Agrawal, B. and Agrawal, C. M., Engineering Drawing, Tata McGraw Hill Publishers&lt;br> • Anilkumar, K. N., Engineering Graphics, Adhyuth Narayan Publishers&lt;br> • Benjamin, J., Engineering Graphics, Pentex Publishers&lt;br> • Bhatt, N., D., Engineering Drawing, Charotar Publishing House Pvt Ltd.&lt;br> • Duff, J. M. and Ross, W. A., Engineering Design and Visualization, Cengage Learning,2009&lt;br> • John, K. C., Engineering Graphics, Prentice Hall India Publishers&lt;br> • Kulkarni, D. M., Rastogi, A. P. and Sarkar, A. K., Engineering Graphics with AutoCAD,PHI 2009&lt;br> •Luzadder, W. J. and Duff, J. M., Fundamentals of Engineering Drawing, PHI 1993&lt;br> • Parthasarathy, N. S., and Murali, V., Engineering Drawing, Oxford University Press&lt;br> • Varghese, P. I., Engineering Graphics, V I P Publishers&lt;br> • Venugopal, K., Engineering Drawing &amp; Graphics, New Age International Publishers</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="engineering_mechanics">
        <item>Statics: Fundamental concepts and laws of mechanics – Rigid body – Principle of transmissibility of forces&lt;br>&lt;br> Coplanar force systems - Moment of a force – Principle of moments&lt;br>&lt;br> Resultant of force and couple system&lt;br>&lt;br> Equilibrium of rigid body – Free body diagram – Conditions of equilibrium in two dimensions – Two force and three force members.</item>
        <item>Types of supports – Problems involving point loads and uniformly distributed loads only.&lt;br>&lt;br> Force systems in space – Degrees of freedom – Free body diagram – Equations of equilibrium – Simple resultant and Equilibrium problems.</item>
        <item>Properties of planar surfaces – Centroid and second moment of area (Derivations not required) - Parallel and perpendicular axis theorem – Centroid and Moment of Inertia of composite area.&lt;br>&lt;br> Polar Moment of Inertia – Radius of gyration – Mass moment of inertia of cylinder and thin disc (No derivations required).&lt;br>&lt;br> Product of inertia – Principal Moment of Inertia (conceptual level).&lt;br>&lt;br> Theorems of Pappus and Guldinus.</item>
        <item>Friction – Characteristics of dry friction – Problems involving friction of ladder, wedges and connected bodies.&lt;br>&lt;br> Definition of work and virtual work – Principle of virtual work for a system of connection bodies – Problems on determinate beams only.</item>
        <item>Dynamics: Rectangular and Cylindrical co-ordinate system&lt;br>&lt;br> Combined motion of rotation and translation – Concept of instantaneous centre – Motion of connecting rod of piston and crank of a reciprocating pump.&lt;br>&lt;br> Rectilinear translation – Newton’s second law – D’Alembert’s Principle – Application to connected bodies (Problems on motion of lift only).</item>
        <item>Mechanical vibrations – Free and forced vibration - Degree of freedom.&lt;br>&lt;br> Simple harmonic motion – Spring-mass model – Period – Stiffness Frequency – Simple numerical problems of single degree of freedom.&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>&lt;b>Text Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Shames, I. H., Engineering Mechanics - Statics and Dynamics, Pearson Prentice&lt;br> • Timoshenko, S. &amp; Young D. H., Engineering Mechanics, McGraw Hill&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Babu, J., Engineering Mechanics, Pearson Prentice Hall&lt;br> • Beer and Johnson, Vector Mechanics for Engineers - Statics and Dynamics, Tata McGraw Hill Publishing Company Limited&lt;br> • Benjamin J., Engineering Mechanics, Pentex Book Publishers and Distributors&lt;br> • Bhavikkatti, S. S., Engineering Mechanics, New Age International Publishers&lt;br> • Hibbeler, R. C., Engineering Mechanics: Statics and Dynamics. Pearson Prentice Hall&lt;br> • Kumar, K. L., Engineering Mechanics, Tata McGraw Hill Publishing Company Limited&lt;br> • Merriam J. L. and Kraige L. G., Engineering Mechanics – Vol. I and II, John Wiley&lt;br> • Rajasekaran S. and Sankarasubramanian, G., Engineering Mechanics, Vikas Publishing House Private Limited&lt;br> • Tayal, A. K., Engineering Mechanics- Statics and Dynamics, Umesh Publications</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="engineering_physics">
        <item>Harmonic Oscillations: Differential equation of damped harmonic oscillation, forced harmonic oscillation and their solutions- Resonance, Q factor, Sharpness of resonance- LCR circuit as an electrical analogue of Mechanical Oscillator (Qualitative)&lt;br>&lt;br> Waves: One dimensional wave - differential equation and solution. Three dimensional waves - Differential equation &amp; its solution. (No derivation) Transverse vibrations of a stretched string.&lt;br>&lt;br></item>
        <item>Interference: Coherence. Interference in thin films and wedge shaped films (Reflected system) Newton’s rings-measurement of wavelength and refractive index of liquid Interference filters. Antireflection coating.&lt;br>&lt;br> Diffraction Fresnel and Fraunhofer diffraction. Fraunhofer diffraction at a single slit. Plane transmission grating. Grating equation - measurment of wavelength. Rayleigh’s criterion for resolution of grating- Resolving power and dispersive power of grating.</item>
        <item>Polarization of Light: Types of polarized light. Double refraction. Nicol Prism. Quarter wave plate and half wave plate. Production and detection of circularly and elliptically polarized light. Induced birefringence- Kerr Cell - Polaroid &amp; applications.&lt;br>&lt;br> Superconductivity: Superconducting phenomena. Meissner effect. Type-I and Type-II superconductors. BCS theory (qualitative). High temperature superconductors - Josephson Junction - SQUID- Applications of superconductors.</item>
        <item>Quantum Mechanics: Uncertainty principle and its applications- formulation of Time dependent and Time independent Schrödinger equations- physical meaning of wave function- Energy and momentum Operators-Eigen values and functions- One dimensional infinite square well potential .Quantum mechanical Tunnelling (Qualitative)&lt;br>&lt;br> Statistical Mechanics: Macrostates and Microstates. Phase space. Basic postulates of Maxwell- Boltzmann, Bose-Einstein and Fermi Dirac statistics. Distribution equations in the three cases (no derivation). Fermi Level and its significance.</item>
        <item>Acoustics: Intensity of sound- Loudness-Absorption coefficient - Reverberation and reverberation time- Significance of reverberation time- Sabine’s formula (No derivation) -Factors affecting acoustics of a building.&lt;br>&lt;br> Ultrasonics: Production of ultrasonic waves - Magnetostriction effect and Piezoelectric effect - Magnetostriction oscillator and Piezoelectric oscillator - Detection of ultrasonics - Thermal and piezoelectric methods- Applications of ultrasonics - NDT and medical.</item>
        <item>Laser: Properties of Lasers, absorption, spontaneous and stimulated emissions, Population inversion, Einstein’s coefficients, Working principle of laser,Optial resonant cavity. Ruby Laser, Helium-Neon Laser, Semiconductor Laser (qualitative). Applications of laser, holography (Recording and reconstruction)&lt;br>&lt;br> Photonics: Basics of solid state lighting - LED – Photodetectors - photo voltaic cell, junction &amp; avalanche photo diodes, photo transistors, thermal detectors, Solar cells- I-V characteristics - Optic fibre-Principle of propagation-numerical aperture-optic communication system (block diagram) - Industrial, medical and technological applications of optical fibre. Fibre optic sensors - Basics of Intensity modulated and phase modulated sensors.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Aruldhas, G., Engineering Physics, PHI Ltd.&lt;br> • Beiser, A., Concepts of Modern Physics, McGraw Hill India Ltd.&lt;br> • Bhattacharya and Tandon, Engineering Physics , Oxford India&lt;br> • Brijlal and Subramanyam, A Text Book of Optics, S. Chand &amp; Co.&lt;br> • Dominic and Nahari, A Text Book of Engineering Physics, Owl Books Publishers&lt;br> • Hecht, E., Optics, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Mehta, N., Applied Physics for Engineers, PHI Ltd&lt;br> • Palais, J. C., Fiber Optic Communications, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Pandey, B. K. and Chathurvedi, S., Engineering Physics, Cengage Learning&lt;br> • Philip, J., A Text Book of Engineering Physics, Educational Publishers&lt;br> • Premlet, B., Engineering Physics, Mc GrawHill India Ltd&lt;br> • Sarin, A. and Rewal, A., Engineering Physics, Wiley India Pvt Ltd&lt;br> • Sears and Zemansky, University Physics , Pearson&lt;br> • Vasudeva, A. S., A Text Book of Engineering Physics, S. Chand &amp; Co&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>Web:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> www.physics.org&lt;br> www.howstuffworks.com&lt;br> www.physics.about.com</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="graphics_weight">
        <item>Module I - 20%</item>
        <item>Module II - 20%</item>
        <item>Module III - 20%</item>
        <item>Module IV - Internal</item>
        <item>Module V - 20%</item>
        <item>Module VI - 20%</item>
        <item>Text Book &amp; References</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_chemical_engineering">
        <item>Introduction to Chemical Engineering: history of Chemical Engineering, role of Chemical Engineering– a broad overview; chemical industries in India; introduction to Chemical Engineering profession; introduction to chemical plant operation; process development and process design.</item>
        <item>Basic concepts: units and dimensions, systems of units, conversion and conversion factors of units, concept of mole, weight percent, mole percent, normality, molarity, molality, vapor pressure, partial pressure, concept of ideal gas and equations of state.</item>
        <item>Overview of unit operations such as distillation, evaporation, absorption, adsorption, extraction, crystallization, drying, leaching, size separation and size reduction. Overview of unit processes like saponification, polymerization, biodiesel formation and hydrogenation.</item>
        <item>Modes of heat transfer-principles of conduction, convection and radiation, heat exchangers. Fluid flow- laminar and turbulent flow. Introduction to transportation of fluids.&lt;br>&lt;br> Classification of chemical reactions, order of reaction, rate equation, Arrhenius equation, conversion and yield, batch reactor, mixed reactor and plug flow reactor.</item>
        <item>Block diagram, process flow diagram for DCDA process for Sulphuric acid manufacture, basic concepts of P&amp;I diagram. Introduction to process instrumentation and control: common methodologies of measurements, measuring instruments: thermocouple, venturimeter, U-tube manometer, elements of feedback control loop, introduction to control of a distillation column.</item>
        <item>Introduction to safety in chemical process industries – basic concepts, Case study: Bhopal gas tragedy. Introduction to Environmental Engineering - basic concepts, Typical wastewater, air and solid waste management system.Case study: Effect of Aerial Spraying of Endosulfan on Residents of Kasargod, Kerala. Challenges of Chemical Engineer –need for sustainable alternatives for processes; products with environment friendly life-cycle. Introduction to novel materials and their development.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Badger and Banchero, Introduction to Chemical Engineering, McGraw Hill&lt;br> • McCabe, W. L., Smith, J.C. and Harriott, P., Unit Operations in Chemical Engineering, McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Pushpavanam, S., Introduction to Chemical Engineering, PHI Learning Pvt. Ltd.&lt;br> • Smith, R., Chemical Process Design and Integration, Wiley Course Plan</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_civil_engineering">
        <item>General introduction to Civil Engineering - History of Civil Engineering - Relevance of Civil Engineering in the overall infrastructural development of the country.&lt;br>&lt;br> Types and classification of structures - buildings, towers, chimneys, bridges, dams, retaining walls, water tanks, silos, roads, railways,runways and pipelines (Brief description only)&lt;br>&lt;br> Definition and types of buildings as per National Building Code of India (brief description only).&lt;br>&lt;br> Selection of site - Components of a building and their functions - Setting out of a building.</item>
        <item>Stones: Classification of stones - Qualities of good building stones - Quarrying - Dressing - Tests - Specifications - Uses of common building stones.&lt;br>&lt;br> Bricks: Composition of good brick earth - Classification - Qualities good bricks - Field and laboratory tests - Specifications.&lt;br>&lt;br> Tiles: Classification - Manufacture - Properties - Tests - Specifications</item>
        <item>Cement: Basic Ingredients – Manufacturing process - Grades - Properties - Tests - Specifications.&lt;br>&lt;br> Aggregates: Fine and coarse aggregate - Properties - Uses - Tests.&lt;br>&lt;br> Cement Mortar: Types and preparation.</item>
        <item>Stone Masonry: Types - Details of Ashlar, Random Rubble, Coarse Rubble and Dry Rubble Masonry.&lt;br>&lt;br> Brick Masonry: Types - Bond - Introduction to all types of bonds - English bond in detail (1, 11⁄2 and 2 brick walls) - Comparison of stone and brick masonry.</item>
        <item>Timber: Properties - Uses - Classification - Seasoning - Defects - Preservation - Tests; Hard board and Particle board - Manufacture and use.&lt;br>&lt;br> Steel: Structural steel and steel as reinforcement - Types - Properties - Uses - Market forms.</item>
        <item>Floors and Flooring materials: Different types and selection of floors and floor coverings.&lt;br>&lt;br> Roofs and roof coverings: Different types of roofs - Suitability - Types and selection of roofing materials.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Chen, W. F. and Liew, J. Y. R., (Eds.), The Civil Engineering Handbook, Second Edition, CRC Press (Taylor and Francis)&lt;br> • Dalal, K. R., Essentials of Civil Engineering, Charotar Publishing House&lt;br> • Gopi, S., Basic Civil Engineering, Pearson Publishers&lt;br> • Kandya, A. A., Elements of Civil Engineering, Charotar Publishing house&lt;br> • Mamlouk, M. S. and Zaniewski, J. P., Materials for Civil and Construction Engineering, Pearson Publishers.&lt;br> • McKay, W. B. and McKay, J. K., Building Construction Volumes 1 to 4, Pearson India Education Services&lt;br> • Rangwala, S. C. and Dalal, K. B., Engineering Materials, Charotar Publishing house&lt;br> • Rangwala, S. C. and Dalal, K. B., Building Construction, Charotar Publishing house</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_computing_and_problem_solving">
        <item>&lt;b>Introduction to digital computer–&lt;/b> Von Neumann concept – A simple model of computer, acquisition of data, storage of data, processing of data, output of processed data. Details of functional units of a computer. Storage – primary storage and secondary storage.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(The discussion should focus more on the functionalities of the units and their interaction than on specific hardware details. However, concepts like memory cells and their addressability (need not be binary), registers, inter connections (buses) have to introduced at an abstract level. For storage devices – primary and secondary –, various categories have to be introduced along with their distinguishing features. For I-O devices also, various categories are to be introduced. The Von Neumann concept should be effectively introduced. History computers need not be taught. However, students have to be encouraged to read the relevant sections of the text book. Chapters 1 – 4 of ‘Goel’ may be used to support teaching -learning.)&lt;/i>&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>Introduction to programming languages:-&lt;/b> types of programming languages - high level language , assembly language and machine language, System software - Operating systems – objectives of operating systems, compiler, assembler and interpreter.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(For all the above topics, focus should be more on the concepts, significance and objectives. Chapter 6 and 7 (up to 7.4) of ‘Goel’ may be used to support the teaching-learning process.)&lt;/i></item>
        <item>&lt;b>Problem Solving strategies –&lt;/b>Problem analysis – formal definition of problem – Solution – top- down design – breaking a problem into sub problems- overview of the solution to the sub problems by writing step by step procedure (algorithm) - representation of procedure by flowchart - Implementation of algorithms – use of procedures to achieve modularity.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(For this part the instructor has to initially use suitable analogies of real world problems to explain the concepts, before delving into computer solvable problems.)&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>Examples for algorithms and flow charts -&lt;/b> at least 10 problems (starting with non-numerical examples, and numeric problems like factorial, largest among three numbers, largest among N, Fibonacci etc.; &lt;i>to be introduced with progressive levels of difficulty) must be discussed in detail. (Class assignments and/or tutorials may be used to strengthen understanding of this part. Chapters 4 and 5 of the ‘Rajaraman’ may be used for the teaching-learning process.)</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Introduction to Python –&lt;/b>variables, expressions and statements, evaluation of expressions, precedence, string operations&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(Note:- the instructor can demonstrate simple programs to the students and encourage them to develop similar ones. In particular, before attempting programs containing functions, the students should be given enough support and time to develop python code containing long sequence of statements for the simple flowcharts developed earlier. This will strengthen the students’ understanding of instruction sequencing. Chapters 1 and 2 of ‘Downey’ have to be covered. Chapter 1 &amp; 2 of ‘Lambert’ can also be used.)&lt;/i> Control statements, Boolean expressions and logical operators, conditional and alternative executions &lt;i>(Note: - Chapter 4 of ‘Downey’ up to Section 4.9 has to be covered. The instructor should demonstrate each of these concepts with real examples and encourage students to develop as many as possible. Chapter 3 of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study) Iteration - while statement and tables. (Note: - Chapter 6 of ‘Downey’ has to be covered. Chapter 3 of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study.)&lt;/i></item>
        <item>Functions, calling functions, type conversion and coercion, composition of functions, mathematical functions, user-defined functions, parameters and arguments.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(Note: - Chapter 3 of ‘Downey’ has to be covered. The instructor should demonstrate each aspect of the function with real examples and encourage students to develop their own. Chapter 6 (up to 6.3) of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study.)&lt;/i></item>
        <item>Strings and lists – string traversal and comparison with examples.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(Note: - Chapter 7 of ‘Downey’ has to be covered. Section 4.1 of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study.)&lt;/i> List operations with examples&lt;i> (Note: - Chapter 8 of ‘Downey’ up to Section 8.6 has to be covered. Section 5.1 of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study.);&lt;/i> tuples and dictionaries – operations and examples &lt;i>(Note: - Chapters 9 &amp; 10 of the third text have to be covered. Section 5.4 of ‘Lambert’ can be used for detailed discussion and self-study.)&lt;/i></item>
        <item>Files and exceptions - text files, directories&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(Note: - Chapter 11 of ‘Downey’ has to be covered)&lt;/i> Introduction to classes and objects - attributes, instances &lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;i>(Note: - Chapter 12 of ‘Downey’ up to Section 12.6 has to be covered)&lt;/i>]</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Text Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Downey, A. et al., How to think like a Computer Scientist: Learning with Python, John Wiley, 2015&lt;br> • Goel, A., Computer Fundamentals, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Lambert K. A., Fundamentals of Python - First Programs, Cengage Learning India, 2015&lt;br> • Rajaraman, V., Computer Basics and C Programming, Prentice-Hall India&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Barry, P., Head First Python, , O’ Reilly Publishers&lt;br> • Dromy, R. G., How to solve it by Computer, Pearson India&lt;br> • Guzdial, M. J., Introduction to Computing and Programming in Python, Pearson India&lt;br> • Perkovic, L., Introduction to Computing Using Python, 2/e, John Wiley, 2015&lt;br> • Sprankle , M., Problem Solving &amp; Programming Concepts, Pearson India&lt;br> • Venit, S. and Drake, E., Prelude to Programming: Concepts &amp; Design, Pearson India&lt;br> • Zelle, J., Python Programming: An Introduction to Computer Science, Franklin, Beedle &amp; Associates Inc.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;b>Web links:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • https://archive.org/details/MIT6.00SCS11&lt;br> • https://www.coursera.org/course/pythonlearn</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_electrical_engineering">
        <item>"Fundamental Concepts of Circuit Elements and Circuit variables: Electromotive force, potential and voltage. Resistors, Capacitors, Inductors- terminal V-I relations. Basic Circuit Laws: Kirchhoff's current and voltage laws, analysis of resistive circuits - mesh, node analysis, super mesh and super node analysis. Star delta transformation. Numerical problems."</item>
        <item>Magnetic Circuits: Magneto motive force, flux, reluctance, permeability-comparison of electric and magnetic circuits analysis of series and parallel magnetic circuits, magnetic circuits with air-gaps. Electromagnetic Induction: Faraday’s laws, Lenz’s law, statically and dynamically induced emf, self and mutual inductance, coupling coefficient. Real and Ideal independent voltage and current sources, V-I relations. Passive sign convention. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Alternating current fundamentals: Frequency, Period, RMS and average values, peak factor and form factor of periodic waveforms (pure sinusoidal and composite waveforms). Phasor Concepts, Complex representation (exponential, polar and rectangular forms) of sinusoidal voltages and currents, phasor diagrams, Complex impedance - series and parallel impedances and admittances. Phasor analysis of RL, RC, RLC circuits. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Complex Power: Concept of power factor - active, reactive power and apparent power. Resonance in series and parallel circuits: Energy, bandwidth and quality factor, variation of impedance and admittance in series and parallel resonant circuits. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Three-phase systems: Star and delta connections, three-phase three wire and three-phase four-wire systems, analysis of balanced and unbalanced star and delta connected loads, power in three-phase circuits. Active and Reactive power measurement by one, two, and three wattmeter methods. Numerical problems.</item>
        <item>Wiring systems: Basic concepts of wiring (conduit wiring only), service mains, meter board and distribution board. Earthing: Earthing of installations - necessity of earthing, plate &amp; pipe earthing. Protective devices: protective fuses, MCB, ELCB.</item>
        <item>"&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bhattacharya, S. K., Basic Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineering, Pearson&lt;br> • Bird, J., Electrical Circuit Theory and Technology, Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group&lt;br> • Edminister, J., Electric Circuits, Schaum's Outline Series, Tata McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Hayt, W. H., Kemmerly, J. E., and Durbin, S. M., Engineering Circuit Analysis, Tata McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Hughes, Electrical and Electronic Technology, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Parker and Smith, Problems in Electrical Engineering, CBS Publishers and Distributors&lt;br> • Sudhakar and Syam Mohan, Circuits and Networks Analysis and Synthesis, Tata McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Suresh Kumar, K. S, Electric Circuits and Networks, Pearson Education"</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_electronics_engineering">
        <item>Evolution of Electronics, Impact of Electronics in industry and in society.&lt;br>&lt;br> Resistors, Capacitors: types, specifications. Standard values, marking, colour coding.&lt;br>&lt;br> Inductors and Transformers: types, specifications, Principle of working.&lt;br>&lt;br> Electro mechanical components: relays and contactors.</item>
        <item>Diodes: Intrinsic and extrinsic semiconductors, PN junction diode, barrier potential, V-I characteristics, Effect of temperature. Equivalent circuit of a diode. Piece wise linear model.&lt;br>&lt;br> Specification parameters of diodes and numbering.&lt;br>&lt;br> Zener diode, Varactor diodes, characteristics, working principle of LED, photo diode, solar cell.</item>
        <item>Bipolar Junction Transistors: Structure, typical doping, Principle of operation, concept of different configurations. Detailed study of input and output characteristics of common base and common emitter configuration, current gain, comparison of three configurations.&lt;br>&lt;br> Concept of load line and operating point. Need for biasing and stabilization, voltage divider biasing, Transistor as amplifier, switch, RC coupled amplifier and frequency response&lt;br>&lt;br> Specification parameters of transistors and type numbering</item>
        <item>Junction Field Effect Transistors: Structure, principle of operation, characteristics, comparison with BJT.&lt;br>&lt;br> MOSFET: Structure, principle of operation of Enhancement type MOSFET, Current voltage characteristics, Depletion-type MOSFET.&lt;br>&lt;br> Principle of operation of Photo transistor, UJT, SCR.</item>
        <item>Diode circuits and power supplies: Series and parallel diode circuits, Clippers, Clampers, Voltage multipliers&lt;br>&lt;br> Half-wave and full wave (including bridge) rectifiers, Derivation of Vrms, Vdc, ripple factor, peak inverse voltage, rectification efficiency in each case, capacitor filter, working and design of a simple zener voltage regulator. Block diagram description of a DC Power supply, Principle of SMPS</item>
        <item>Electronic Measurements and measuring Instruments.&lt;br>&lt;br> Generalized performance parameters of instruments: error, accuracy, sensitivity, precision and resolution. Principle and block diagram of analog and digital multimeter, Block diagram of CRO, Measurements using CRO, Lissajous patterns, Principle and block diagram of DSO, function generator.&lt;br>&lt;br> Testing of Electronic components.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Bell, D. A., Electronic Devices and Circuits, Oxford University Press&lt;br> • Boylested, R. L. and Nashelsky, L., Electronic Devices and Circuit Theory, Pearson Education&lt;br> • Kal, S., Basic Electronics: Devices, Circuits and its Fundamentals, PHI Learning &lt;br> • Millman, J., Halkias, C. and Parikhu, C. D., Integrated Electronics, Tata Mc Graw Hill&lt;br> • Neaman, D. A., Electronic Circuits Analysis and Design, McGraw Hill&lt;br> • Sedra, A. S. and Smith, K. C., Microelectronic Circuits, Oxford University Press</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_mechanical_engineering_sciences">
        <item>&lt;b>Thermodynamics:&lt;/b>Nature and scope of thermodynamics; Basic concepts ; Laws of thermodynamics- Discovery, Significance &amp; Applications; Qualitative ideas on Entropy, Available energy, Irreversibility, Clausius Inequality, Principle of increase of entropy &amp; Carnot engine; Limitations of Thermodynamics; Sources of power; history of power production; power production in the future.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Thermal Engineering:&lt;/b> Historical development of steam engine, steam turbines, gas turbines and hydraulic turbines; Principle of turbomachinery; History of IC engines; two stroke and four stroke engines-working, applications; Air compressors- types and uses; Principles of Rocket propulsion, chemical rockets, Indian space programme</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Refrigeration &amp; Air Conditioning:&lt;/b> History &amp; scope of refrigeration; applications of refrigeration; Food preservation, refrigerated storage; applications in chemical and process industries; special applications; Air conditioning- Principles &amp; systems; scope of air conditioning; Components of A/c systems, all-air and all-water A/c systems;, Psychrometric properties of air; Human comfort; comfort standards.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Automobile &amp; Aeronautical Engineering:&lt;/b> Introduction to an Automobile; history of the automobile; Indian Automobiles; Types of automobiles; Layout of an automobile; Major components and their functions; Manufacturers of motor vehicles in India; Fundamentals of aerodynamics; theory of lift and drag; aircraft engines-types and applications.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Mechanisms &amp; Machines:&lt;/b> Introduction; Analysis and synthesis; terminology; definitions &amp; assumptions; planar, spherical and spatial mechanisms, examples of mechanisms; mobility; classification of mechanisms; Grashof’s law; mechanical advantage; Mechanical Engineering design; types of design; design considerations; types of loads; factor of safety; codes &amp; standards; economics of design; reliability; safety.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Manufacturing Engineering &amp; Materials:&lt;/b> Introduction and history of materials and manufacturing; engineering materials; metals, alloys, composites, microstructures, heat treatment, physical properties of materials and material testing; methods of manufacturing; examples of manufactured products; Computer Integrated manufacturing; lean production &amp; agile manufacturing; environmentally conscious design &amp; manufacturing; organization for manufacture.</item>
        <item>&lt;b>References Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Dossat, R. J., Principles of Refrigeration, PHI&lt;br>&lt;br> • Heywood, J., Internal Combustion Engine Fundamentals, McGraw Hill Publishers&lt;br> • Holman, J. P., Thermodynamics, McGraw Hill Co.&lt;br> • Jain, K. K. and Asthana, R. B., Automobile Engineering, TTTI Bhopal&lt;br> • Kalpakjian, S. and Schmid, S. R., Manufacturing Processes for Engineering Materials, Pearson education&lt;br> • Maines, R., Landmarks in Mechanical Engineering, ASME&lt;br> • Menon, R. V. G., The Development of Science &amp; Technology.&lt;br> • Peng, W. W., Principles of Turbomachinery, John Wiley &amp; Sons&lt;br> • Pita, E. G., Air Conditioning Principles &amp; Systems, PHI&lt;br> • Shigley, J. E. and Uicker, J. J., Theory of Machines &amp; Mechanisms, Oxford University Press&lt;br> • Shigley, J. E., Mechanical Engineering Design, McGraw Hill Publishers&lt;br> • Spalding, D. B. and Cole, E. H., Engineering Thermodynamics, ELBS &amp; Edward Arnold (Pub) Ltd.&lt;br> • Stone, R. and Ball, T. K., Automotive Engineering Fundamentals, SAE International&lt;br> • Sutton, G. P. and Ross, D. M., Rocket Propulsion Elements, John Wiley &amp; Sons&lt;br> • Von Karman, T., Aerodynamics: Selected Topics in the Light of Their Historical Development, Courier Corporation&lt;br> • Online course on Refrigeration &amp; Air conditioning, IIT Kharagpur www.nptel.ac.in</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="introduction_to_sustainable_engineering">
        <item>Sustainability - Introduction, Need and concept of sustainability, Social environmental and economic sustainability concepts. Sustainable development, Nexus between Technology and Sustainable development, Challenges for Sustainable Development. Multilateral environmental agreements and Protocols - Clean Development Mechanism (CDM), Environmental legislations in India - Water Act, Air Act.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do at least one project eg:&lt;br> a) Identifying/assessment of sustainability in your neighbourhood in education, housing, water resources, energy resources, food supplies, land use, environmental protection etc.&lt;br> b) Identify the threats for sustainability in any selected area and explore solutions for the same</item>
        <item>Air Pollution, Effects of Air Pollution; Water pollution- sources, Sustainable wastewater treatment, Solid waste - sources, impacts of solid waste, Zero waste concept, 3 R concept. Global environmental issues- Resource degradation, Climate change, Global warming, Ozone layer depletion, Regional and Local Environmental Issues. Carbon credits and carbon trading, carbon foot print.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do at least one project for eg:&lt;br> a) Assessing the pollution status of a small area&lt;br> b) Programmes for enhancing public environmental awareness&lt;br> c) Observe a pond nearby and think about the different measures that can be adopted for its conservation</item>
        <item>Environmental management standards, ISO 14000 series, Life Cycle Analysis (LCA) - Scope and Goal, Bio-mimicking, Environment Impact Assessment (EIA) - Procedures of EIA in India.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do at least one project eg:&lt;br> a) Conducting LCA of products (eg. Aluminium cans, PVC bottles, cars etc.or activities (Comparison of land filling and open burning)&lt;br> b) Conducting an EIA study of a small project (eg. Construction of a building)</item>
        <item>Basic concepts of sustainable habitat, Green buildings, green materials for building construction, material selection for sustainable design, green building certification, Methods for increasing energy efficiency of buildings. Sustainable cities, Sustainable transport.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do at least one project eg:&lt;br> a) Consider the design aspects of a sustainable building for your campus&lt;br> b) Explore the different methods that can be adopted for maintaining a sustainable transport system in your city.</item>
        <item>Energy sources: Basic concepts-Conventional and non-conventional, solar energy, Fuel cells, Wind energy, Small hydro plants, bio-fuels, Energy derived from oceans, Geothermal energy.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do at least one project eg:&lt;br> a) Find out the energy savings that can be achieved by the installation of a solar water heater&lt;br> b) Conduct a feasibility study for the installation of wind mills in Kerala</item>
        <item>Green Engineering, Sustainable Urbanisation, industrialisation and poverty reduction; Social and technological change, Industrial Processes: Material selection, Pollution Prevention, Industrial Ecology, Industrial symbiosis.&lt;br>&lt;br> Students may be assigned to do a group project eg:&lt;br> a) Collect details for instances of climate change in your locality&lt;br> b) Find out the carbon credits you can gain by using a sustainable transport system (travelling in a cycle or car pooling from college to home)&lt;br> c) Have a debate on the topics like: Industrial Ecology is a Boon or Bane for Industries?/Are we scaring the people on Climate Change unnecessarily?/Technology enables Development sustainable or the root cause of unsustainability?</item>
        <item>&lt;b>Reference Books:&lt;/b>&lt;br>&lt;br> • Allen, D. T. and Shonnard, D. R., Sustainability Engineering: Concepts, Design and Case Studies, Prentice Hall.&lt;br> • Bradley. A.S; Adebayo,A.O., Maria, P. Engineering applications in sustainable design and development, Cengage learning&lt;br> • Environment Impact Assessment Guidelines, Notification of Government of India, 2006&lt;br> • Mackenthun, K.M., Basic Concepts in Environmental Management, Lewis Publication, London, 1998&lt;br> • ECBC Code 2007, Bureau of Energy Efficiency, New Delhi Bureau of Energy Efficiency Publications-Rating System, TERI Publications - GRIHA Rating System&lt;br> • Ni bin Chang, Systems Analysis for Sustainable Engineering: Theory and Applications, McGraw-Hill Professional.&lt;br> • Twidell, J. W. and Weir, A. D., Renewable Energy Resources, English Language Book Society (ELBS).</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="question_papper_subjects">
        <item>Basics of Civil Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Electrical Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Electronics Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Mechanical Engineering Sciences</item>
        <item>Calculus</item>
        <item>Differential Equations</item>
        <item>Engineering Graphics</item>
        <item>Engineering Physics</item>
        <item>Design and Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Sustainable Engineering</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="subjects">
        <item>Calculus</item>
        <item>Engineering Physics</item>
        <item>Engineering Chemistry</item>
        <item>Engineering Mechanics</item>
        <item>Engineering Graphics</item>
        <item>Introduction to Civil Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Mechanical Engineering Sciences</item>
        <item>Introduction to Electrical Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Electronics Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Computing and Problem Solving</item>
        <item>Introduction to Chemical Engineering</item>
        <item>Introduction to Sustainable Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Civil Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Mechanical Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Electrical Engineering</item>
        <item>Basics of Electronics Engineering</item>
        <item>Differential Equations</item>
        <item>Design and Engineering</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>
